American College of Neuropsychopharmacology Records Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
American College of Neuropsychopharmacology Records
1961 - 1984
This collection contains records from the American College of Neuropsychopharmacology. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
American College of Neuropsychopharmacology
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1981.0001
The records of the American College of Neuropsychopharmacology were donated in 1981 and 1984 through the organization’s Secretariat.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
The College was founded in 1961 as a professional society in brain, behavior, and psychopharmacology research. It is a non-profit, tax exempt, scientific professional organization whose members are drawn from the fields of psychiatry, psychology, pharmacology, neurophysiology, neurochemistry, biochemistry and internal medicine. Its members are selected for membership to ACNP by their peers, primarily on the basis of their original scholarly contributions to the field of neuropsychopharmacology, which involves the evaluation of the effects of synthetic compounds or natural products upon the brain and human behavior.
The primary function of ACNP is to serve as a forum for the exchange of scientific information regarding the pharmacology, toxicology, and clinical application of neuropsychopharmacological agents. ACNP members have testified as expert witnesses in the trials of major cases, worked jointly with various administrative agencies and executive departments, and testified before Congress on numerous legal, ethical, and scientific issues relating to neuropsychopharmacology and national health policy. Many of the federal government’s expert advisors on the use of antipsychotic and neurological substances and their potential for abuse are members of the ACNP. The College has annual meetings and conducts study groups and plenary sessions in addition to publishing a bulletin quarterly. The ACNP bestows the Daniel Ebron award for outstanding research in the field.
The officers of the College are the President, President-Elect, Vice-President, Secretary-Treasurer, Assistant Secretary-Treasurer, and a Council consisting of the above-named officers, including the last retired President and five other members. The Council transacts all business of the College, including the approval or disapproval of all recommendations of committees, and determines dues structure and adopts rules and regulations for the election of the various classes of membership. Among its responsibilities, the Council creates and directs standing committees and elects editors and committees on publications. In 2008, the College placed its archives at the Louise M. Darling Biomedical Library at UCLA.
American College of Neuropsychopharmacology; Neuropsychopharmacology; Psychopharmacology
The collection primarily consists of printed or mimeographed material; very little original correspondence is included in these records. The collection is comprised of the constitution and by-laws, the minutes of the Council and business meetings that took place at the annual meetings, programs pertaining to the annual meetings, abstracts of papers, workshops and posters presented at the annual meetings, published bulletins, and membership directories. Also included are information letters sent by the Secretariat to the members. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Council and business meeting minutes, 1964 - 1971 (Box 1)
  - Council and business meeting minutes, 1972 - 1975 (Box 1)
  - Council and business meeting minutes, 1976 - 1981 (Box 1)
  - Annual meeting program bulletins, 1962; 1973 - 1983 (Box 1)
  - Abstracts of papers, workshops, and posters presented at the annual meetings, 1980 - 1983 (Box 1)
  - Bulletin, 1963 - 1967 (Box 2)
  - Bulletin, 1968 - 1972 (Box 2)
  - Membership directories, 1978; 1983 - 1984 (Box 2)
  - Secretariat, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Secretariat, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Reports, “Combined Maoi-Tricyclic Antidepressant Treatment; A Reevaluation” Brief for the U.S. Supreme Court as Amicus Curiae on Boston State Hospital case and “Anxiety Reconceptualized” by Donald Klein, 1980 (Box 2)